Finding Aid for the Powell Family Papers LSC.0230
UCLA Library Special Collections
Powell Family papers
1836-1961
UCLA Library Special Collections
Powell family
LSC.0230
19.0 Linear Feet (38 boxes and 4 oversize boxes)
George Harold Powell (1872-1922) was born in Ghent, New York. The U.S. Department of Agriculture sent him to California in 1904 to study citrus fruits rotting in transit. In 1896, he married Gertrude Eliza Clark (1870-1957). They had three sons, Harold Clark Powell (1900-1938), George Townsend Powell (1901-1955), and Lawrence Clark Powell (1906- ), who became the Librarian of the UCLA Library, Director of the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, and dean of the School of Library Service at UCLA. The collection consists of correspondence, diaries, journals, manuscripts, memorabilia, books, scrapbooks, and printed materials related to the Powell family. The bulk is made up of the papers and correspondence of George Harold Powell, horticulturist and general manager of the California Fruit Exchange (1912-22) and his wife, Gertrude Clark Powell.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lawrence Clark Powell, 1965.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9927229053606533
Biography
George Harold Powell was born in 1872 in Ghent, New York, on February 8, 1872; BS (1895) and MS (1896), Agriculture, Cornell; pomologist, Bureau of Plant Industry, Washington, D.C., 1901-1911; U.S. Department of Agriculture sent him to California in 1904 to study citrus fruits rotting in transit; general manager, California Fruit Exchange (today known as Sunkist Growers), 1912; married Gertrude Eliza Clark (1870-1957) on July 1, 1896; they had three sons, Harold Clark Powell (1900-1938), George Townsend Powell (1901-1955), and Lawrence Clark Powell (1906- ), who became the Librarian of the UCLA Library, Director of the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, and dean of the School of Library Service at UCLA; George Harold Powell died of a heart attack on Feb. 18, 1922 in Pasadena, California.
Biographical Narrative
The Powell Family Papers consist predominately of the correspondence and papers of George Harold Powell (1872-1922) and Gertrude Clark Powell (1870-1957). George Harold Powell was born to George Townsend Powell (1843-1927) and Marcia Alger Chace Powell (1845-1932) at Ghent, New York, on February 8, 1872. His father was one of the leading horticulturalists of New York State and was noted especially for his apples. Both of his parents were Quakers. His grandparents were Townsend and Catherine Macy Powell. George Harold Powell attended public schools and the Union Free High School in Chatham, New York. He also attended Cornell University where obtained a B.S. and M.S. in agriculture in 1895 and 1896 respectively.
In 1896 Powell was appointed Horticulturalist at the Experiment Station of Delaware Agricultural College in Dover. September 1901 found him in Washington, D.C., as assistant pomologist in the Bureau of Plant Industry, U.S. Department of Agriculture, studying problems of cold storage in connection with the apple industry. He was appointed pomologist in charge of fruit storage and transportation investigations in 1904. The Department of Agriculture sent George Powell to California in the same year at the request of the California orange growers for an investigation of the rotting of citrus fruits in transit. At that time he met Ethan Allen Chase (1832-1921), a pioneer in the citrus industry at Riverside. He made a trip to Europe in 1908 to study the fruit industry there. In 1909 he was appointed assistant chief of the Bureau of Plant Industry and in 1911 he was made acting chief but resigned to accept the position of secretary and manager of the California Citurs Protective Leaque. After another trip to Europe, he was appointed General Manager of the California Fruit Growers Exchange, now known as Sunkist Growers, in September 1912.
George Harold Powell's most influential work, Cooperation in Agriculture, was published in 1913. It soon became the standard work on this subject. Mr. Powell was one of the chief exponents of cooperation in marketing agricultural produce. When the United States entered World War I, he was called to Washington to take charge of the Perishable Food Division of the U.S. Food Administration. There he worked with Herbert Hoover (1874-1964) who was the head of the U.S. Food Administration. In recognition of his outstanding service, George Harold Powell was awarded the Cross of Chevalier of the Order of the Crown by King Albert of Belgium.
In 1919 Powell returned to his position at the California Fruit Growers Exchange. In January 1922 he served as chairman of the committee on marketing farm products at the National Agriculture Conference called by President Harding. He also delivered a notable address on Fundamentals of Cooperative Marketing. While attending a dinner at the Hotel Maryland in Pasadena on February 18, 1922, George Harold Powell died of a heart attack. A public memorial was held at the Morosco Theatre in Los Angeles at which Herbert Hoover, then Secretary of Commerce, delivered the principal address. On April 25, 1923 the Memorial Tablet of the Late George Harold Powell was presented to the U.S. Department of Agriculture by the former members of the Division of Perishable Foods of the U.S. Food Administration.
George Harold Clark married Gertrude Eliza Clark on July 1, 1896 in the Friends Meeting House at Collins, New York. Gertrude Clark Powell was born at Cornwall-on-Hudson, New York, on October 18, 1870. She was the eldest of three children borne to Quaker parents, William Henry Clark (1844-1913), a Buffalo lawyer, and Mary Lawrence Haines Clark (1844-1896). Her grandparents were Phebe Lawrence Haines (1819-1892) and Jesse Hartley Haines (1814-1902). Gertrude Clark Powell attended high school in Buffalo and went on to Cornell University. She graduated in the Class of 1895 with her husband. She was a member of Alpha Phi and Phi Beta Kappa.
Gertrude Clark Powell and George Harold Powell's first son, Harold Clark Powell (1900-1938), was born in Newmark, Delaware, on February 16, 1900. With his father and grandfather, Harold Clark Powell represented three generations of leading horticulturalists. He received his education from Michigan State College, East Lansing, and the University of California. After working in the fruit industry in California, he received an appointment as Professor of Horticulture at the Transvaal University College, University of South Africa in Pretoria. In five years he had acquired such a reputation that the Empire Marketing Board asked him to visit the colonies and to report on their citrus potentialities. The standard textbook in the Union of South Africa on citrus was his The Culture of the Orange and Allied Fruits. At the time of his accidental death in 1938, practically every citrus expert in the Union was trained by him and the whole field staff of the Citrus Exchange had been very much influenced by him.
Gertrude Clark and George Harold Powell's second son, George Townsend Powell (1901-1955) was born in Washington, D.C. The third son, Lawrence Clark Powell (1906-) was also born in Washington. Lawrence Clark Powell entered the library profession. In 1944 he was appointed Head Librarian at the UCLA Library and Director of the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library. In 1960 he became Dean of the School of Library Service at UCLA. He relinquished the title of University Librarian in June 1961, but continued as the Director of the Clark Library. Additional information about Lawrence Clark Powell's contributions to the UCLA Library and the library profession can be found in the Records of the Office of the Librarian, B 18, Series 9, and in other entries under Powell, Lawrence Clark, in the Numbered Collections Catalog as well as in the Lawrence Clark Powell Papers, Collection Number 229.
The papers of other families related to the George Harold Powell family are also included in the Powell Family Papers. For an understanding of the relationships of the various members of these families, the family trees by Marian Clark Cooch and Lawrence Clark Powell will provide the basic information. Briefly, however, the Lawrence and the Haines families are related to the Clark family which joined the Powell family when Gertrude Clark Powell married George Harold Powell. These families have a long Quaker tradition. It is, therefore, fitting that the family copy of George Fox's Journal, printed and sold by Sowle in 1694, should be in this collection. The collection also includes some correspondence from and material about Elizabeth Powell Bond (1841-1926), Dean of Swarthmore College. One of the outstanding features of these papers is the many photographs of members of the family and other persons. There are several autographed photographs of Herbert Hoover as well as a photographic album of the members of the U.S. Food Administration, Division of Perishable Foods, 1917-1919. Also of note are the journals and diaries of Gertrude Clark Powell covering the years from 1893 to 1957.
Also included in the Powell Family Papers are the papers of Harold Haines Clark (1878-1964), the brother of Gertrude Clark Powell. He was very close to the George Harold Powell family, especially after the death of Mr. Powell. He was associated with the Link Belt Company for thirty years and became the Manager of its Pacific Coast Division.
The Powell Family Papers were given to the UCLA Department of Special Collections as a continuing gift of Dean Lawrence Clark Powell in 1955. The gift is to be concluded in 1964 with the papers of Harold Haines Clark.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, diaries, journals, manuscripts, memorabilia, books, scrapbooks, and printed materials related to the Powell family. The bulk is made up of the papers and correspondence of George Harold Powell, horticulturist and general manager of the California Fruit Exchange (1912-22) and his wife, Gertrude Clark Powell. Also includes the papers of Harold Haines Clark, brother of Gertrude Clark Powell, who was associated with the Link Belt Company. The papers of the Lawrence and Haines families are related to the Clark family and these family papers include a copy of George Fox's Journal (1694) and some material about and from Elizabeth Powell Bond, dean of Swarthmore College. Also autographed photographs of Herbert Hoover and a photo album of the members of the U.S. Food Administration, Division of Perishable Foods, 1917-19.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence of George Harold Powell.
Correspondence of Gertrude Clark Powell.
Papers of George Harold Powell.
Papers of Gertrude Clark Powell.
Papers of Harold Clark Powell.
Papers of the Powell-Lawrence-Haines-Clark families.
Papers of the Powell family.
Papers of the Clark family.
Papers of the Haines family.
Papers of the Lawrence family.
Papers of Marian Lawrence Clark Cooch.
Papers of Harold Haines Clark.
George Harold Powell and Powell family scrapbooks, diaries, and photographs.
Bible.
Family papers.; Horticulturists -- California, Southern -- Archives.; Bond, Elizabeth Powell; Bond, Elizabeth Powell, 1841-1926--Archives.; California Fruit Growers Exchange; Clark, Harold Haines, 1878-1964--Archives.; Fox, George; Powell, George Harold -- Archives; Hoover, Herbert -- Photographs; Powell, Gertrude Eliza Clark -- Archives; Powell, Harold Clark -- Archives; Powell family -- Archives; Clark, Harold Haines
- Correspondence of George Harold Powell
  - Business and Personal Letters
    - Letters from Various Persons
      - 1900-1916 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Ethan Allen Chase
      - 1909-1920. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence With Various Persons Regarding the U.S. Food Administration
      - 1917-1918. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence of Various Persons Other Than George Harold Powell Regarding the U.S. Food Administration
      - 1917-1920 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Family Correspondence
    - Letters to His Wife, Gertrude Clark Powell
      - 1904-1906. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - August-October 1908. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - March-May 1909. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - June-August 1909. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - 1913. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 1918. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters to His Children
      - 1911-1916. (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 1917. (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - 1918. (Box 2, Folder 2a)
      - 1919 and n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2b)
    - Letters from His Children
      - 1909-1918. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence With Various Members of the Family
      - 1895-1914. (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - 1916-1922 and n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Letters to Both George Harold Powell and Gertrude Clark Powell
      - 1900-1915 and n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence of Gertrude Clark Powell
  - Personal Correspondence
    - Letters to Various Relatives
      - 1873-1905. (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - 1931. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - 1932. (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - January-July 1933. (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - August-December 1933. (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - 1934 and n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Letters from Her Father, William Henry Clark
      - 1880-1924 and n.d. (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Her Father-in-Law, George Townsend Powell
      - 1922-1926 and n.d. (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Letters from Her Mother, Mary Lawrence (Haines) Clark
      - 1884-1892. (Box 33, Folder 3)
      - 1893-1894 and n.d. (Box 33, Folder 4)
      - 1895-1929. (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Her Sister, Marian Lawrence (Clark) Cooch
      - 1902-1950. (Box 33, Folder 6)
      - 1951-1952. (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Letters from Her Brother, Harold Haines Clark and from Her Sister-in-Law, Emma (Holbrook) Clark
      - 1900-1950. (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Letters from Various Relatives
      - 1891-1948 and n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Various Persons and Distant Relatives
      - 1900-1927. (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - 1930-1939. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - 1940-1948. (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - 1949-1957. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Family Correspondence
    - Letters to Her Son, Lawrence Clark Powell
      - 1925-1926. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - 1930-1931. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - 1930-1931. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - 1932. (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - 1936-1937. (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - 1936-1937. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - 1941-1951. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - 1953-1954. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Letters from Her Son, Harold Clark Powell
      - 1912-1918. (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - January-April 1919. (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - May-December 1919. (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - 1921-1926. (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - 1928. (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - 1929. (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - 1930-1938. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Letters from Her Daughter-in-Law, Margaret Carey Powell
      - 1921-1928. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - 1929. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - 1930-1935. (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - 1936-1938. (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - 1939-1948. (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Gertude C. Powell: Various letters., 1924-1942. (Box 41, Folder 3)
        Scope and Contents note
        To Margaret Carey Powell Hargraves, H. Clark Powell, Marcia Hargreaves, as well as letters from LCP.
      - H. Clark and Margaret Powell: Various letters., 1924-1932. (Box 41, Folder 4)
        To Gertrude Clark Powell, H. Clark to Margaret.
      - H. Clark and Margaret Powell: Various letters to Mrs. Gertrude C. Powell, from Mrs. George L. Powell, 1926-1931. (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Her Daughter-in-Law, Marjorie Leslie Powell
      - 1932-1941. (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - 1942-1952 and n.d. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Letters from Her Granddaughter, Marcia Virginia Powell
      - 1928-1952 and n.d. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Her Grandson, David Clark Powell
      - 1940-1946 and n.d. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Letters from Her Grandson, William Clark Powell
      - 1950-1951. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Her Son, George Townsend Powell Including Some from His Wife, Edwina Martin Powell
      - 1912-1939. (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - 1940-1950 and n.d. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Her Son, Lawrence Clark Powell
      - 1912-1929. (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - 1930-1932. (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - 1933-1935. (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - 1936-1940. (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - 1941-1950. (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - 1951-1957. (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Her Daughter-in-Law, Fay Shoemaker Powell
      - 1940-1954 and n.d. (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Her Grandson, Wilkie Haines Powell
      - 1950-1951. (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Letters to and from Various Persons
      - 1900-1961. (Box 34, Folder 6)
- Papers of George Harold Powell
  - Diaries, Address Books, etc.
    - Autograph Book and Address Book., 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Diary. and Memo Day Book kept by George harold Powell while in Europe., 1908 1909.; 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 2a)
    - Last will of G. Harold Powell. (Box 8, Folder 2b)
  - Publications and Writings
    - A Defense of the Indian. Chatham Union School., 1891.; Typescript with corrections. 5pp. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Cover Crops and Soil Conditions in Orchards., February 4, 1902.; Typescript with corrections. 7pp. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Experiments of the U.S. Department of Agriculture in Cold Storage., January 28-29, 1903.; Typescript with corrections. 9pp. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Practical Difficulties in the Cold Storage of Apples. U.S. Department of Agriculture., August 5, 1903.; Typescript with corrections. 12pp. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - The Apple in Cold Storage. U.S. Department of Agriculture., November 11, 1903.; Carbon copy typescript. 14pp. (Box 8, Folder 7)
      General note
      (The following is an outline of an illustrated talk by Mr. Powell on the above subject)
    - Summary of Lecture by G. Harold Powell, Pomologist in Charge of Fruit Storage Investigations. U.S. Department of Agriculture, Washington, D.C. Before the Maine State Pomological Society, Auburn, Maine., November 11, 1903.; Carbon copy typescript. 3pp. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Apple in Cold Storage. U.S. Department of Agriculture., November 18, 1903.; Carbon copy typescript. 3pp. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - The Decay of Oranges while in Transit from California, By G. Harold Powell [and others] Washington, Government Printing Office. (U.S. Department of Agriculture. Bureau of Plant Industry. Bulletin no.123)., 1908; 79pp. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Cooperation in Agriculture. New York: Macmillan. xv., 1913.; 327pp. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Fundamental Principles of Co-operation in Agriculture. University of California. College of Agriculture. Agricultural Experiment Station. Circular no.222., October 1920.; 24pp. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Ethan Allen Chase, An Appreciation., December 1921.; [A small unpaged pamphlet] 4 copies. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Bibliography of the writings of George Harold Powell., 3 × 5" cards. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Publications about G. Harold Powell and the Citrus Industry
    - Citrus Protective League of California. The Decay in Citrus Fruits while in Transit. Los Angeles., February 4, 1911.; 3pp. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Citrus Protective League of California. The Prevention of Decay in Citrus Fruits. Los Angeles., February 18, 1911.; 4pp.
    - Collins, James H.
      - The Biggest Marketing Exchange, California Citrus Organization and Its Manager. The Country Gentleman, vol.81, no.3 () pp.3-4 + Collins, James H., January 15, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Marketing California Citrus, Sales Methods that Dispose of 30,000 Cars. The Country Gentleman, vol.81, no.3 () pp.6-7., January 29, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Crissey, Forrest
      - The Crop Scout. The Saturday Evening Post () pp.24-26 +., November 19, 1910 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Francisco, Don
      - G. Harold Powell, An Appreciation., Carbon copy typescript. 9pp. (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - The Story of Sunkist Advertising, Transcript of a Talk by Mr. Don Francisco before the Apprentice Group of the J. Walter Thompson Company, New York City., December 9, 1948.; Mimeographed typescript. 23pp. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Fulton, Sanford H.
      - G. Harold Powell. The California Citrograph () pp.372, 407-408., September 1923 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - _____ _____ A photostatic copy. (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - G. Harold Powell. In Interesting People, The American Magazine. pp.424, 425-26. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Holman, Charles W.
      - Keeping Faith with the Consumer. Technical World Magazine., pp.531-537. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - MacCurdy, Rahno Mabel
      - The History of the California Fruit Growers Exchange. Los Angeles., 1925.; 106pp. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Mills, Minnie Tibbets
      - Luther Calvin Tibbets, Founder of the Navel Orange Industry of California. The Quarterly, Historical Society of Southern California. vol.25, no.4 ()., December 1943; pp.127-161. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Ritchie, Robert Welles
      - The Religion of Cooperation; the California Citrus Growers' Pride in his Association and his Trade-mark. The Country Gentleman (, September 4, 1920.; pp.13, 41. (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - There's a Limit to Pooling; Danger Threatens When the Public's Interest Is Ignored. The Country Gentleman () pp.3-4, 5., August 27, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - They Took a Tip from Big Business; California Farmers Moved Their Citrus and Walnut Crops by 'Delivered Sales'. The Country Gentleman ()., July 30, 1921; pp.1-2. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Sunkist Growers
      - The Story of California Oranges and Lemons. Los Angeles, California Fruit Growers Exchange, c., 1943.; 30pp. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Webber, H.J.
      - An Appreciation of G. Harold Powell. The California Countryman ()., April 1922; pp.13, 17. (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Who's Who--And Why. Noted Men and Women of the Southwest. Illustrated Weekly ()., November 16, 1912; p.7. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Woehlke, Walter V.
      - In the Orange Country, Where an Orchard Is a Mine. The Human Factor Among the Gold-bearing Trees of California. Sunset ()., March 1911; pp.251-264. 2 copies. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Materials and correspondence., 1942-1948. (Box 9, Folder 6)
      re a proposed biography of G. Harold Powell by Lawrence Clark Powell.
    - A selected bibliography of articles about G. Harold Powell., 3 × 5 cards. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Articles appearing in Newspapers. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Clippings. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Book. Riverside, California, The Press(?) Printing Company., 1912.; Photocopy. (Box 9, Folder 11)
      Celebration in honor of the eighteith birthday of Ethan Allan Chase of Riverside, California at the Chase Plantation, Corona, January the Eighteenth, Nineteen Hundred and Twelve.
    - Scrapbook--Begins with work in California., 1909. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Scrapbook., 1904-1909. (Box 30)
      (Shelved at the end of the collection)
  - Memorabilia
    - Class of Ninety-five, Cornell University. Ithaca, New York., June 1895.; 103pp. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Class of 1895, Cornell University Class List. Compiled by Erle W. Whitefield and William F. Atkinson. [n.p.], 1912.; 61pp. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Menus, etc. of dinners attended by G. Harold Powell. Includes the autograph album of the dinner given by Mr. Joseph H. Steinhardt for G. Harold Powell in New York., December 17, 1921. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Photographs
    - Christmas cards showing the Herbert Hoover Residence and the Don Francisco Family. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Autographed photographs of Herbert Hoover. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - G. Harold Powell in his early years. (Box 10, Folder 6)